Finding Aid for the Lawrence Durrell Papers LSC.0637
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lawrence Durrell papers
1934-1966
UCLA Library Special Collections
Durrell, Lawrence
LSC.0637
3 Linear Feet (6 boxes and 1 oversize box)
Collection consists of materials related to Durrell's career as a writer. Includes correspondence, literary manuscripts, drawings, photographs, sound recordings, and books. Correspondence includes letters to various persons and correspondence between Lawrence Clark Powell and others regarding the Durrell collection. Manuscripts include an 1886 translation of Pope Joan: the female Pope.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9912179043606533
Biography
Lawrence George Durrell was born Feb. 27, 1912 in Julundur, India; the son of British parents, he grew up in India and spent his young adult years in England; he held many odd jobs such as jazz pianist, automobile racer, real estate agent, instructor, and press attaché; moved to France and became a full time writer in 1957; of his various publications, Durrell is best known for the Alexandria quartet, a tetralogy with titles, Justine, Balthazar, Mountolive, and Clea which appeared between 1957 and 1960; died Nov. 7, 1990.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials related to Durrell's career as a writer. Includes correspondence, literary manuscripts, drawings, photographs, sound recordings, and books. Correspondence includes letters to various persons and correspondence between Lawrence Clark Powell and others regarding the Durrell collection. Manuscripts include an 1886 translation of Pope Joan: the female Pope.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence (1934-1966), drawings and photographs (Box 1).
Manuscripts of poems, stories, articles, and plays by Lawrence Durrell (Box 2).
Manuscripts of Pope Joan (Box 3).
Manuscripts of novels and printed books by Lawrence Durrell (Box 4).
Printed material relating to Lawrence Durrell (Box 5).
Books from the library of Lawrence Durrell (Box 6).
Related Material
Henry Miller papers (Collection 110). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Letters to Henry Miller, 1935-1968, from various places.
352 items.
Holograph and typescript. Many of these letters were published in Lawrence Durrell [and] Henry Miller; a private correspondence. Edited by George Wickes. New York, Dutton, 1963.
Kenneth Rexroth papers (Collection 175). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Manuscripts for publication; Authors, English -- 20th century -- Archives; Durrell, Lawrence--Archives.
- Correspondence; Drawings, and Photographs., 1934-1966
  - Letters to Terence Ian Armstrong (pseudonym John Gawsworth), from Sussex and Corfu., 1934-1937; 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Terence Ian Armstrong (pseudonym John Gawsworth), from Paris, Innsbruck, and London., 1937-1939; 15 items. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Terence Ian Armstrong (pseudonym John Gawsworth) ,from Egypt, England, Argentina, and Yugoslavia., 1943-1951; 12 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Jean Franchette,, mostly from Nimes., 1955-1959; 37 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Jean Franchette,, mostly from Nimes., 1960-1961; 20 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Jean Franchette, and undated, mostly from Nimes., 1962; 12 items. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Theodore Stephanides,, from Corfu, Paris, and Innsbruck., 1936-1938; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Theodore Stephanides,, from Athens and Alexandria., 1939-1945; 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Theodore Stephanides,, from Rhodes and Argentina., 1946-1948; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Theodore Stephanides,, from Belgrade., 1949-1953; 27 items. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Theodore Stephanides,, from Cyprus and England., 1953-1956; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Theodore Stephanides,, from France and Corfu., 1957-1965; 26 items. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Theodore Stephanides,, from France., 1966; 6 items. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to J. Tambinuttu from Alexandria, Rhodes, Argentina, and England., 8 items. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence with Michael Frankel, Peter Owen, Spencer Curtis Brown, Covici-Friede, Maurice Girodias, Alfred Pérlès, George Wickes, Ivan Zarian, Osbert Sitwell, Terence Tiller, and Alan Thomas., 39 items. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Lawrence Clark Powell,, including letters from Rhodes, Bournemouth, Argentina, and Provence., 1946-1966; 26 items. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence between Lawrence Clark Powell and various persons regarding the Durrell Collection,., 1947-1960; 67 items. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Drawings and watercolors by Durrell and Nancy Durrell, including watercolor with photograph of Durrell, inscribed "To Henry with love and good wishes; Larry Durrell." "Paris, 1938."; 13 items. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Lawrence Durrell and his family., 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Manuscripts of poems, stories, articles, and plays by Lawrence Durrell.
  - Faces. [London, 1934] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    4 l. Typescript. Dedication to John Gawsworth on first l. signed by Durrell. Poem with five verses.
  - The cherries, n.p.,., ca 1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    6 l. 26 cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. First published in "Masterpiece of Thrills," Daily Express, London, 1936.
  - A Christmas carol. Corfu, [1936] (Box 2, Folder 3)
    1 p.1, 22 l. 28 cm. Typescript. Later published under title "Asylum in the Snow" in Seven, No. 3 (Winter 1938), 49-54; also in Zero and Asylum in snow. Two Excursion into Reality. Rhodes, 1946, privately printed.
    Another copy. 1 p.1., 21 l. 27 cm. Typescript (carbon copy).
  - Ionian profile, by Charles Norden. London., September 31, [1936 or 1937] (Box 2, Folder 4)
    2 l. Galley proofs. Appeared in Time and Tide, London, September 31, 1936 or 1937. Dedicated to Theodore Stephanides.
  - Down the Styx in an air-conditioned canoe. Paris,., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    1 p.1., 10 l. 26 cm. Typescript. Published in The Booster, II (December 1937 - January 1938), 14-17. Signed by the author.
  - Hamlet, prince of China. Corfu, [1937] (Box 2, Folder 6)
    9 l. Typescript. Letter addressed to Henry Miller regarding the book Hamlet by Michael Frankel and Henry Miller. Published in Delta, 2c année, No. 3, Christmas 1938.
  - A hymn to the Pycnik for Henry Miller, Paris,., 1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    4 p. Holograph. At head: "MS for Henry Miller of Paris gent. Feb. 9th 1938," Poem with seven verses.
  - Proems. London, Fortune Press, [1938] (Box 2, Folder 8)
    96 p. illus. 19 cm. Contains Lawrence Durrell's "Unckebunck" with holograph revisions for projected radio adaptation. Bound in black morocco. Inscribed by Lawrence Durrell.
  - Black honey; an historical farce. [Alexandria, ca 1942] (Box 2, Folder 9)
    1 p.1., 50 l. 33 cm. Typescript (carbon copy). Bound in green cloth spring binder.
  - Cities, plains, and people; poems. London, Faber & Faber, [1945] (Box 2, Folder 10)
    63 l. 18 cm. Page proofs with holograph corrections. Bound in gray cloth with black morocco spine. First published by Faber & Faber, London, 1946.
  - On seeming to presume. Argentina, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    1 p.1., 15 l. Galley proofs. First published by Faber & Faber, London, 1948. In blue and gray morocco box. Gift of Bill McKeown to Lawrence Clark Powell, 1948.
  - Another copy with holograph letter to Henry Miller on p.1. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Henry Miller, n.p.,., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    12 l. 28 cm. Typescript.
  - For immediate release. Cyprus,., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    14 l. 33 cm. Holograph. Published as chapter in Esprit de Corps; Sketches from Diplomatic Life; London, Faber & Faber, 1957.
  - Sappho. n.p.,., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    2 p.1., 61 l. 33 cm. Typescript with corrections, cuts, etc. in producer's hand for radio version, 1957. First published by Faber & Faber, London, 1950.
  - The willpower man. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    1 p.1., 19 p. 33 cm. Holograph manuscript. Purchased from the House of Books, 18 E 60th Street, New York.
  - Kavaphis, Konstantinos Petro, .Translations from the poems of Kavaphis of Alexandria, [by] Lawrence Durrell., 1863-1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    1 p.1.,11 l. 22 cm. Typescript.
- Manuscripts of Pope Joan.
  - Rhoïdes, Emmanuel D.,., 1835-1904 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Pope Joan, by Emmanuel Royidis. Translated from the Greek with an introduction by Lawrence Durrell. n.p., ca 1948. 2 p.1., 83 l. 33 cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. Bound in red linen with a red morocco backstrip.
  - Preface and notes to Emmanuel Rhoïdees' Pope Joan, by Lawarence Durrell. n.p.,., ca 1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    2 p.l., 11, 7 [1] l. 33 cm. Typescript with a few holograph corrections to the preface.
    Bibliography
    Bibliography: final leaf.
  - Rhoïdes, Emmanuel D.,., 1835-1904 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Pope Joan. Translated from the Greek Lawrence Durrell. n.p., ca 1948. 36 l. 64 cm. Galley proofs, partially corrected by Theodore Stephanides.
  - Later copy with corrections in red ink by Theodore Stephanides. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rhoïdes, Emmanuel D.,., 1835-1904 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    [Pope Joan] The curious history of Pope Joan. Translated out of the modern Greek of Emmanuel Royidis by Lawrence Durrell and illustrated by John Buckland-Wright. 13 illustrations. London, Rodney Phillips and Green, 1948. xxii, 134 p. 26 cm. Bibliography: p. 134. Unbound copy on mould-made paper. Never issued. The firm of publishers who planned it went out of business before the book could be produced. There was to have been an edition limited to 150 on mould-made paper. First published by Derek Verschoyle, London, 1954. Subsequent editions published, 1960 and 1961.
  - Miscellaneous additional page proofs. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Prospectus with text and illustrations issued by Rodney Phillips and Green. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Buckland-Wright, John. Illustrations for the curious history of Pope Joan, by Emmanuel Royidis, translated out of the modern Greek by Lawrence Durrell. London, Rodney Phillips and Green, [1948] (Box 3, Folder 8 and 9)
    Includes: series of 15 pencil and pen-and-ink drawings, some in wash. 14 l., 27 x 21 cm; 5 pen-and-ink drawings, original jacket design, and 2 copies of jacket.
  - Rhoïdes, Emmanuel D.,., 1835-1904 (Box 3)
    [Pope Joan] The curious history of Pope Joan, by Emmanuel Royidis. Translated out of the modern Greek by Lawrence Durrell and illustrated by John Buckland-Wright. 13 illustrations, London, Rodney Phillips and Green [1948] xxiv, 134 p. 25 cm. Page proofs. Proofs cut and mounted in gray linen with maroon backstrip.
    Most illustrations on Neg. Microfilm # 06596 - see shelf list for details
  - Rhoïd#x0113;s, Emmanuel D.,., 1835-1904 (Box 3)
    Pope Joan; the female Pope. Translated from the Greek of Emmanuel Rhoïdes with preface by Charles Hastings Collette. London, George Redway, 1886. 102 p. 19 cm. Bound in red cloth.
  - Buckland-Wright, John. Illustrated title page for The curious history of Pope Joan, by Emmanuel Royidis, translated out of the modern Greek by Lawrence Durrell. London, Rodney Phillips and Green [1948] Printer's engraved plate mounted on wood. (Box 3)
- Manuscripts of novels and printed books by Lawarence Durrell.
  - Cefalu. [In three parts] Rhodes,., 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    4 p.1., 151 [2] l.28 cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. First published by Editions Poetry, London, 1947. Later published, 1958, under title: The Dark Labyrinth. Gift of Friends of the UCLA Library, 1962, in honor of Lawrence Clark Powell.
  - Balthazar; a second Justine. In two parts. n.p.,., ca 1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    5 p.l., 180 l. 27 cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. First published by Faber & Faber, London, 1957.
  - Tunc. London, Faber & Faber,., 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    316 l. illustrated. 20 cm. Page proofs with holograph corrections. First published by Dutton, New York, 1968. Gift of Henry Miller, June,1969.
  - Quaint fragment. [London] Cecil Press,., 1931 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    [38] p. Mounted port. Photocopy. Los Angeles, 1951.
  - A landmark gone. Los Angeles, Private print,., 1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    1 p.1., 11, 7 [1] p. 21 ½ cm. Title in black and green. "First published in Middle East Anthology, London, 1946." "125 copies printed by Reuben Pearson... for the friends of Lawrence Clark Powell." "A note on Lawrence Durrell" (p. [1] - ii) signed: L.C.P. [Lawrence Clark Powell].
- Printed material relating to Lawrence Durrell.
  - Poems by Durrell. Clippings from newspapers, photo reproductions, and typed copies., 8 items. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Articles and prefaces by Durrell. Clippings from newspapers and journals and typed copies., 11 items. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Monitor. [Television script of an interview between Durrell and Weldon]. London, British Broadcasting Corporation,., Feb. 14, 1960; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    6 l. 32 ½ cm. Mimeographed. Gift of Robert Collison, July, 1960.
  - Extract from tonight. [Television script of an interview between Durrell and Hart]. London, British Broadcasting Corporation,., June 23, 1960; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    2 l. 32 ½ cm. Mimeographed. Gift of Robert Collison, August, 1960.
  - Periodical articles and extracts from books on Durrell and his works., 17 items. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to Durrell and his works., 52 items. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper articles and programs relating to the German production of Actis in Hamburg,., November, 1961; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper articles and programs relating to the German production of Durrell's Sappho at Hamburg, and to the British premiere of Sappho at the Edinburgh Festival,., November, 1959, August, 1961; 10 items. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper articles and programs relating to the production of Durrell's Sappho at the Edinburgh Festival,., August, 1962; 11 items. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Book jackets of Durrell's works., 12 items. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Booksellers' catalogs and brochures advertising Durrell material., 34 items. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified printed and manuscript materials., 6 items. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Books from the library of Lawrence Durrell.
  - Catullus Tibullus and Pervigilium Veneris. London, Heineman; Cambridge, Harvard University Press,., 1950 (Box 6)
    Durrell's bookplate on first p.1. Signed "Lawrence Durrell, Moharram Bey, Alexandria."
  - Dostoevsky, Fyodor. Letters of Fyodor Michailovitch Dostoevsky to his family and friends, translated by Ethel Colburn Mayne. London, Chatto and Windus,., 1914 (Box 6)
    Contains Durrell's bookplate. Signed "Lawrence Durrell, Moharram Bey, Alexandria."
    General note
    missing 1/5/81
  - Freud, Anna. The psycho-analytical treatment of children. London, Imagos., 1946 (Box 6)
    Contains Durrell's bookplate. Signed "Lawrence Durrell, Bellepoix in Cyprus '55."
  - Humphreys, Christine, Zen Buddhism. London, Heineman., 1949 (Box 6)
    Contains Durrell's bookplate. Signed "Lawrence Durrell, Bellepoix Abbey, Cyprus, gift from H. M."
  - Miller, Henry. Big Sur and the oranges of Hieronymus Bosch. New York, New Directions,., 1957 (Box 6)
    Inscribed "Patricia Rodda from Lawrence Durrell, Sommieres Gard, France '57."
  - The Portable Plato. New York, Viking,., 1948 (Box 6)
    Contains Durrell's bookplate. Signed "Lawrence Durrell, Belgrade."
  - Books in the collection from the library of Lawrence Clark Powell (Box 6)
    - Spencer, Bernard. Aegean Islands and other poems. London, Editions Poetry,., 1946; 2 copies. (Box 6)
      Ex Libris: Lawrence Clark Powell.
    - Webster and Ford. Plays. London, J.M. Dent, New York, Dutton. Signed "LC Powell, Bournemouth,, Gift of Alan Thomas,", 1951 (Box 6)
    - Wickes, George, editor. Lawrence Durrell and Henry Miller, a private correspondence. New York, E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc.,., 1965 (Box 6)
      Presentation copy to Lawrence Clark Powell from George Wickes, Lawrence Durrell and Henry Miller. Enclosed are two signed cards from the authors.
    - Oversize packages Original painting in poster colours on blue paper of the harbour and town of Kyrenia in Cyprus. Signed "Larry." (Box 7)